How did this small country manage to
survive and avoid being invaded during
World War II? Right in the heart of a
burning Europe and completely surrounded
by the Third Reich and its allies? Well,
there are several reasons and the first
one, of course, is geography.
Switzerland is literally hidden in the
mountains. Its territory is covered by
the Alps, and the mountain passes act as
natural fortresses. Despite this,
Switzerland understood that it couldn't
match the Third Reich in manpower and
military equipment. So in response to
Hitler's invasion plan, the country
developed its own defense plan, not to
hold the borders, but to fall back deep
into the inaccessible Alps, where
hundreds of forts, tunnels, and bunkers
were ready and every bridge and railway
was mined. It was clear that the
invasion of Switzerland would have been
too costly, and the country had
something more valuable to offer, its
neutrality. Back in 1815, right after
the Napoleonic Wars, Switzerland
officially declared its permanent
neutrality. And since then, it hasn't
taken part in any of the more than a 100
military conflicts in Europe. When the
war began, the currency of Nazi Germany
and its allies was no longer accepted
anywhere in the world. So, Swiss banks
became a convenient way to convert
currency into Swiss Franks and use them
in international trade. Moreover, a
large portion of the gold looted by the
Nazis was also sold to Switzerland, then
melted it down and resold it as neutral
Swiss gold. This controversial but
long-standing neutrality is directly
linked to the unique decentralization of
power. Switzerland is made up of 26
cantons, each functioning almost like an
independent state. It's the world's
largest country with no official capital
at all and all key functions are spread
across its territory. For example, the
government is based in burn.
International diplomacy is centered in
Geneva. The Supreme Court is located in
Loausanne and the National Bank is in
Zurich.